In the last video, we trained an animal deformer that can apply vertex deltas based on pose changes.
지난 영상에서는 포즈 변화에 따라 버텍스 델타를 적용하는 ML 디포머를 학습시켰습니다.
Now, what if I want to control muscle activation independently?
이번에는 근육 활성화를 포즈와 독립적으로 제어하고 싶다면 어떻게 할까요?
For example, horses sometimes can contract glute muscles while standing still.
예를 들어 말은 가만히 서 있어도 둔근을 수축시키는 경우가 있습니다.
In the Witcher 4 tech demo, we controlled muscle activation with animation curves.
위쳐 4 테크 데모에서는 애니메이션 커브로 근육 활성화를 제어했습니다.
I'm going to show you how to do that by using our email example.
지금부터 에밀(Emil) 예제를 사용해 그 방법을 보여드리겠습니다.
So let's go ahead and go back to our email flesh asset.
먼저 에밀의 Flesh 에셋으로 돌아가겠습니다.
And because we're working with the lower pectoralis and also the bicep,
이번에는 하부 대흉근(lower pectoralis)과 이두근(bicep)을 다룰 것이므로,
let's go ahead and start creating some animation curves.
애니메이션 커브를 몇 개 만들어보겠습니다.
Let's locate our skin, scalpel mesh.
스킨용 스켈레탈 메시를 찾습니다.
Open that and then click add curve here.
해당 에셋을 열고 여기서 ‘Add Curve’를 클릭하세요.
So first, let's add the bicep.
먼저 이두근 커브를 추가하고,
And also the lower pec.
하부 대흉근 커브도 추가합니다.
Now we have curves over here.
이제 여기 커브들이 생겼습니다.
We can go back over here and start reading the curves in the skeletal mesh.
이제 돌아가서 스켈레탈 메시의 커브를 읽어들이도록 하겠습니다.
So let's go ahead and save this.
우선 이 상태를 저장하고,
And back here, let's call a node called read skeletal mesh curves.
여기서 ‘Read Skeletal Mesh Curves’ 노드를 호출합니다.
What this will do is that we'll read the skeletal mesh curves and then save it to our flesh asset to build the connection.
이 노드는 스켈레탈 메시의 커브를 읽어서 Flesh 에셋에 저장해 연결을 만들어 줍니다.
So over here, let's give it the skeletal mesh that we just worked on.
방금 작업한 그 스켈레탈 메쉬를 여기에 지정하고,
As we do that, we can import skeletal mesh chains.
그럼 스켈레탈 메시 체인들을 가져올 수 있습니다.
You can see now two curves has been have been imported.
보시다시피 커브 두 개가 가져와졌습니다.
See one is a bicep, one is a lower pec.
하나는 이두근, 다른 하나는 하부 대흉근이죠.
And make sure we connect collection here.
그리고 여기 컬렉션 연결을 잊지 마세요.
But over here in muscle name, we have to draw the association between the curve and the muscle so that the curve knows which muscle is controlling.
하지만 여기 Muscle Name에서, 각 커브가 어느 근육을 제어하는지 알 수 있도록 근육과의 연결(Association)을 지정해야 합니다.
We can do that if we grab the muscle mesh.
이를 위해 해당 근육 메쉬를 선택하면 됩니다.
Let's visualize here.
여기서 시각화해 보죠.
Let's first do the bicep.
먼저 이두근부터 하겠습니다.
So if you click the bicep, it will show you the name of the mesh in the scene outliner.
이두근을 클릭하면 씬 아웃라이너에 해당 메쉬 이름이 표시됩니다.
So let's make sure we grab this one.
이걸 정확히 선택해 주세요.
It's called SKM, email, upper body muscles, split mesh 58, 10, 15, 10.
이름은 ‘SKM_Emil_UpperBody_Muscles_SplitMesh_58_10_15_10’처럼 되어 있습니다.
So now if we go to our read skeletal mesh curves, we should be able to see the exact mesh name here.
이제 ‘Read Skeletal Mesh Curves’ 쪽에서도 동일한 메쉬 이름을 볼 수 있어야 합니다.
58, 57.
58, 57.
So let's make sure we copy that down.
이 값을 복사해 두고,
And for now, we can only type it in.
현재는 수동으로 입력해야 합니다.
It's called SKM, email, upper body muscles.
이름은 ‘SKM_Emil_UpperBody_Muscles’이고,
Split mesh, 58, 57.
SplitMesh_58_57 입니다.
So in the future, we should add the feature that will allow us to copy the name directly from the scene outline.
나중에는 씬 아웃라이너에서 이름을 직접 복사할 수 있는 기능을 추가할 예정입니다.
So for the bicep, let's do that.
이두근에 대해 이렇게 설정해 주고,
And then same thing for the pectoralis.
대흉근도 같은 방식으로 설정합니다.
Find it, 28, 27.
해당 이름은 28, 27입니다.
Let's go back over here.
다시 이쪽으로 돌아와서,
Copy that.
복사해 넣고,
And hit 28, 27.
28, 27로 입력합니다.
Great.
좋습니다.
And now make sure you click assign skeletal mesh curves to muscles.
그리고 ‘Assign Skeletal Mesh Curves To Muscles’를 눌러 주세요.
Now this will build the connection between the animation curve and muscles.
이제 애니메이션 커브와 근육 간의 연결이 생성됩니다.
So we can go ahead and go in to muscle activation.
그럼 Muscle Activation 탭으로 넘어가 보겠습니다.
Now here, you should see the muscle association here.
여기서 방금 설정한 근육 연결 정보가 보일 겁니다.
See muscle activation curve name.
근육 활성화 커브 이름도 표시되죠.
So each muscle has a curve associated to it.
즉, 각 근육마다 연결된 커브가 하나씩 있습니다.
And that's good.
잘 설정되었습니다.
Let's connect this back to the terminal so that the flesh asset knows about this information.
이 정보를 Flesh 에셋이 알 수 있도록 터미널에 다시 연결해 줍니다.
Now at this point, let's start generating some training animation for the animation curve ML deformer.
이제 커브 기반 ML 디포머를 위한 트레이닝 애니메이션을 생성해 보겠습니다.
So if you go to ML deformer, you can notice that for the network inputs, it can either be the bones, which means this is a pose driven ML deformer.
ML Deformer 설정을 보면 입력은 두 가지일 수 있습니다. 본(포즈)을 입력으로 쓰면 포즈 기반 ML 디포머가 되고,
Or it could be animation curve that makes this curve driven ML deformer.
애니메이션 커브를 입력으로 쓰면 커브 기반 ML 디포머가 됩니다.
They both apply deltas to vertices, but the input is different.
둘 다 버텍스에 델타를 적용하지만 입력 방식이 다릅니다.
So think about when you have a curve for the bicep, where you can drag it up and down to control muscle contraction in each pose.
예를 들어 이두근에 대한 커브가 있다면, 슬라이더를 위아래로 움직여 각 포즈에서 근육 수축 정도를 조절할 수 있겠죠.
And this will be independent from the pose driven ML deformer.
이 제어는 포즈 기반 ML 디포머와는 독립적으로 동작합니다.
So let's go back here and start generating some training animation.
그럼 돌아와서 트레이닝용 애니메이션을 생성하겠습니다.
The note we'll be calling is called animation or the curve sampling animation asset terminal.
여기서 사용할 것은 ‘Curve Sampling Animation Asset’ 터미널(노드)입니다.
Once you grab that, it takes two inputs.
이 노드는 두 가지 입력을 받습니다.
One is the sculptal mesh asset.
첫 번째는 스켈레탈 메시 에셋이고,
And in this case, it will be the skin that we just worked on.
여기서는 방금 커브를 추가했던 스킨 메시가 대상입니다.
We added two curves to it.
방금 커브 두 개를 추가했죠.
It also takes the animation asset.
두 번째 입력은 애니메이션 에셋입니다.
And let's go ahead and duplicate an animation asset.
애니메이션 에셋을 하나 복제해서,
Choose either one and then it's duplicated.
아무 것이나 선택해 복제합니다.
And I can call this one the activation training data.
복제본의 이름은 ‘Activation_Training_Data’로 하겠습니다.
Awesome.
좋아요.
Let's save this.
저장해 주고,
Then now over here, let's assign the animation asset.
이제 여기서 방금 만든 애니메이션 에셋을 할당합니다.
Choose the training data.
‘Activation_Training_Data’를 선택하세요.
And the purpose of this node is that it will generate some training data and stuff that into this animation asset.
이 노드는 학습용 데이터를 생성해 지정한 애니메이션 에셋 안에 넣어주는 역할을 합니다.
So we won't modify it, basically.
원본을 건드리지 않기 위해 복제본을 사용한 것이죠.
That's why we duplicated the animation asset.
그래서 아까 애니메이션 에셋을 복제한 겁니다.
And for each muscle or each curve, it will generate this number of frames training data.
각 근육(각 커브)마다 여기 설정한 프레임 수만큼 학습 데이터를 만들어 줍니다.
So for now, let's select 30 frame rate and then let's do 20 frames per curve.
이번에는 프레임 레이트를 30, 커브당 20프레임으로 설정하겠습니다.
And then if we evaluate this, we should have the animation asset ready.
이제 실행(Evaluate)하면 애니메이션 에셋이 준비됩니다.
So here you can see we have two curves.
여기 보시면 커브가 두 개 있고,
And then each curve is basically ranging from 0 to 1 in its assigned slot, which is 0 to 20 for the bicep.
각 커브는 할당된 구간에서 0에서 1까지 값을 갖습니다. 이두근은 0~20프레임 구간이고,
And then 20 to 40 for the lower pectoralis.
하부 대흉근은 20~40프레임 구간입니다.
So after that, we can start generating some simulation data on this specific training animation.
이제 이 트레이닝 애니메이션을 대상으로 시뮬레이션 데이터를 생성하겠습니다.
So let's go ahead and do that by setting the animation to the training data one.
애니메이션으로 방금 만든 트레이닝 데이터를 지정하고,
And in this case, it will be 40 frames.
전체 프레임 수는 40프레임이 됩니다.
So that would be roughly 1.34 seconds.
대략 1.34초 정도죠.
And then we need to create a new chaos cache collection.
그리고 새로운 Chaos Cache 컬렉션을 하나 만들어야 합니다.
I'll call this one activation training chaos cache collection.
이름은 ‘Activation_Training_ChaosCache_Collection’으로 하겠습니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
And the last thing we need to remember is that for deactivation.
마지막으로 기억할 점이 하나 더 있습니다.
Now, before we were doing length based muscle activation.
지금까지는 근육 길이에 기반해 자동으로 활성화되도록 했는데,
Basically, you contract muscles whenever the muscles get shorter because of the animation.
즉, 애니메이션으로 근육 길이가 짧아지면 근육이 수축되도록 했습니다.
Now we want to turn that off, but instead override muscle activation animation curves.
이제 그 기능은 끄고, 대신 ‘근육 활성화 애니메이션 커브’로 덮어쓰겠습니다.
Make sure you turn that on.
이 옵션을 켜는 것을 잊지 마세요.
And now it looks good.
이제 설정이 좋아 보입니다.
Make sure we save this and start running the simulation.
저장한 뒤 시뮬레이션을 실행하세요.
Okay, we just finished our simulation.
좋아요, 시뮬레이션이 방금 완료되었습니다.
Now let's look at the simulation results.
결과를 살펴보겠습니다.
You can see from 0 to 20, the bicep starts to contract.
0~20프레임 구간에서 이두근이 수축하기 시작하고,
So it contracts and then it goes off.
수축했다가 다시 꺼집니다.
And then there's a lower pectoralis.
그리고 20프레임 이후에는 하부 대흉근이 동작하죠.
But this is exactly what we want.
바로 우리가 원하던 동작입니다.
And notice that there's no pose change at all.
그리고 포즈 변화는 전혀 없습니다.
We're just using the stationary pose or the wrist pose.
그냥 정지 포즈, 즉 레스트 포즈만 사용했습니다.
And that's enough to train the curved German M-O-deformer.
이것만으로 커브 기반 ML 디포머를 학습하기에 충분합니다.
So let's use this simulation data and generate a geometry cache.
그럼 이 시뮬레이션 데이터를 이용해서 지오메트리 캐시를 생성하겠습니다.
I'll be here.
여기서 진행할게요.
Let's make sure we create a new geometry cache.
새 지오메트리 캐시를 생성하고,
That's good.
좋습니다.
And then generate a geometry cache of the skin.
스킨에 대한 지오메트리 캐시도 만들어 줍니다.
We're going to use the geometry cache to train that M-O-deformer.
이 지오메트리 캐시를 사용해 ML 디포머를 학습시킬 겁니다.
Awesome.
아주 좋아요.
There we go.
됐습니다.
Now this is the skin.
이제 스킨 쪽을 보면,
You see the bicep contracts and then the lower pec contracts.
이두근이 수축하고 이어서 하부 대흉근이 수축하는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
Okay.
좋아요.